Our aim for this project was to design a
Wireless Cardiac Auscultation
and At-Home Monitoring System.
This includes a wearable device that
continuously records the user’s heart sounds
and an accompanying application, where
the user would be able to interact with
the received recordings.
The wireless device consists of a PETG 3D-printed
shell which encloses the battery along with
the custom designed printed circuit board
where the overall size of the device was
kept to a minimum with a
size of 5 x 7 x 2.6 centimetres.
The PCB houses all of the electronic
components including a MEMS microphone and
an ESP32 microcontroller with an antenna.
Designed for direct skin contact, the base of
the enclosure is made from a TPU plastic due to
its hypoallergenic properties with a
cut out for the microphone.
The enclosure is held in a brace that ensures
the microphone maintains a constant contact
with the skin to get the best audio quality
with reduced motion artifacts.
The brace is designed to be worn with the
device for long periods of time while
carrying out daily activities,
therefore must ensure the wearer’s
comfort and device security.
By using elastic bands and a buckle,
the brace can accommodate a range of body
types and still maintain a secure tight fit.
The device is placed on the user’s mitral
point from which it records the heart sounds.
These are sampled at a rate of 1 kHz for
10 seconds at a time using the MEMS microphone
with a calibrated ADC.
The ESP32 microcontroller powering the device
is responsible for carrying out the recording
and storage of the heart sounds on the device
then transferring them over to the application
using Bluetooth Low Energy.
The application handles receiving communication
from the MCU, data storage, data processing,
and user interaction.
The app features 3 sections each designed
to be as user friendly as possible with good
object oriented programming practices
followed throughout, including the use of
design patterns like observer and callback.
From the recordings screen the user can track
and manage all their recordings, including
filtering, sorting, adding/viewing tags, and more.
From the device settings screen the user
can manage the connection with the physical
device including connecting and disconnecting
and setting the recording mode.
In addition, a machine learning model runs in
a background thread of the application and
analyses the recorded heart sounds
to categorise them as either
normal, abnormal or unknown.
The machine learning model is trained on
data classified by expert cardiologists.
It processes each received audio file and
transforms it into a mel-frequency spectrogram,
which allows for the use of a
Convolutional Neural Network.
These models are suited for identifying spatial
patterns, such as heart sound abnormalities.
The model achieves an accuracy of 90% in
healthy and unhealthy classification when
applied to unseen test sets, and around 75%
during real-world deployments.
The project successfully met the aim of creating a
Wireless Cardiac Auscultation
and At-Home Monitoring System
and managed to expand on its goal by
incorporating a machine learning model
and a brace into the project.